I've been building AI agents since 2022,
and in the grand scheme of things,
that's not a lot of time, but for AI
agents, it certainly is. I was super
early on building agents when Chat GBT
was just getting popular. We didn't even
have things like function calling or
other competing LLMs like Claude or
Gemini. And it's gotten to the point
after a few years where I'm now very
confident no matter the agent that I
have to build. But it took a long time
to get there and a lot of very hard
lessons learned along the way. And so
what I am super excited to dive into
right now with you is a clear and simple
process that I would follow today if I
had to learn how to build AI agents from
scratch. And I can guarantee that if you
follow this, you will learn how to build
AI agents 10 times faster than me
skipping all of the hard lessons. And so
no matter your experience level, you can
feel confident building agents for
yourself, your business, or other
people. So with that, let's dive right
into it. So, here is a bird's eyee view
of the path that I would follow right
now if I had to learn how to build AI
agents from scratch. And I'm breaking it
up into 10 different phases. And don't
worry, I'm being quite specific in each
phase. So, it's not like there is a lot
of time that you would have to spend to
go through this process. In fact, even
if you are completely new to AI agents,
you could easily get through everything
here in just a couple of months. And I
will stay pretty high level here as we
go through the phases, but I will call
out videos on my channel that apply to
what we're talking about if you want to
dive deeper into that specific subject.
So with that, let's go ahead and dive
into the first step, which is phase one,
building out our foundation. And this is
starting with the absolute basics like
what is a large language model? Learning
about the best ones out there right now
like Claude or Gemini, GPT, even
learning about local AI. These are large
language models you can run on your own
computer like Mistl or Quinn. And then
also learning AI agents versus
traditional automations. It's a whole
paradigm shift when we add this extra
reasoning into our automations through
AI agents. There's a lot more power but
also unpredictability that comes with
this. And so I have a video right here
where I dive into that. It's really
important to understand that difference.
And then also we get to effective
prompting. learning how to talk to these
large language models and agents. And I
am specifically leaving out the phrase
prompt engineering because I think that
is overused and overhyped, but it still
is really important for us to learn how
to talk to these LLMs just like it's
important for us to learn how to talk to
other people. And then lastly,
leveraging out ofthe-box tools. And so I
want to talk about this right now, even
though this is a path for building our
own agents, because it's important for
you to build an agent that's not just
solving a problem that has already been
solved. And I see this happen a lot
where someone wants to build an AI
agent. They want to automate something
with an LLM, but there's an
out-of-the-box solution that already
does exactly what they need for like $5
a month. So it's like, why invest the
time into building that agent? And so do
your due diligence before you build an
agent, making sure there isn't something
already out there that solves your
problem completely or at least for the
most part. So we have tools like chat
GBT or cloud desktop for your chat
applications. Things like MCP servers,
which is a way to give capabilities very
easily out of the box to our AI agents.
I have a video here where I talk about
that. I'll just show you really quickly
a couple of the AI tools that I use out
of the box. None of these platforms are
sponsoring this video. So, I just want
to show you at least a few of the tools
that I use pretty much on a daily basis.
Starting with Claude Desktop. This is my
go-to application just to quickly have
conversations with an LLM. Bounce ideas
off. And they have support for MCP
servers and other tool integrations to
make it very easy to connect to my other
AI agents. And then along with it, I
like using this platform called Aqua
Voice. So, you can see in the bottom
middle that I'm speaking right now. And
then it can take what I said and turn it
into text in any text box on my entire
computer. Take a look at this. It is
just so powerful. I love using my voice
to quickly communicate, especially to
LLMs. And then also, I love this
platform called MEM. This is my place to
organize all my notes and things like
scripts for my YouTube videos. And they
have a great API to make it very easy to
integrate with my other agents, pretty
much just like Claude Desktop. And then
the last one that I'll show right now is
Perplexity. This is a deep research tool
that I'll use all the time. When there
are new AI tech that comes out, new LLMs
or frameworks that I want to research, I
will use Perplexity for that. So, those
are just a few of the tools that I love
using. The last thing that I'll say here
for phase one is that you always need to
remember capabilities over tools. And
what I mean by that is you want to focus
on what you're able to accomplish
instead of getting into the nitty-gritty
details of mastering specific tools. And
it's so important. This applies to all
the other phases going forward when we
dive into other things like no code
tools or AI coding assistance. You want
to learn the high lever skills that will
carry you far no matter the tool you end
up using. You don't want to get caught
in the weeds spending hours and hours
and hours mastering very specific tools
that might become irrelevant next month.
And I've caught myself doing that all
the time. This is really one of the
biggest tips that I have for you in this
entire video is capabilities over tools.
And I have some very concrete examples
of that going forward as well. And so
that will take us now into the next
phase, which is building AI agents with
no code tools. It doesn't matter if
you're brand new to automating or if you
have a lot of coding experience. I would
still highly recommend starting with
these no code tools. When you learn for
the first time how to build AI agents,
and there are a lot of great platforms
out there for this, like N8N or
Flowwise, other ones like Voice Flow and
Relevance AI. And I still use these
tools all the time. Especially for
prototyping for my AI agents because you
can get your agents up and running so
quickly with these tools. Even if you do
have a lot of coding experience like me,
it's worth using. And this is your time
to learn how you can integrate tools
with your agents so they can do things
on your behalf and your services like
Gmail and Slack and Outlook. Learning
about retrieval augmented generation.
This is a super important process to
give external knowledge into your AI
agents. is essentially making them
domain experts on your documents. And I
cover rag a lot on my channel. Here's a
video specifically where I'm
implementing rag within N8N, which that
is my favorite noode agent builder. So
definitely check that out if you're
interested. Also, learning about basic
agent memory is really important in this
phase. We see it all the time with
applications like chat GBT and Claude
Desktop where the agent is able to
remember the conversation and previous
messages that we sent. But it's
important for you to understand how that
works and how that data is stored in our
database. And lastly, I'm a very
hands-on learner. And honestly, I
believe pretty firmly that everyone is.
You don't get a lot out of a college
course, for example, when you just have
to read through a textbook and take a
bunch of tests. And I've been there,
done that. I always learn a lot more
when I actually do something. And so,
I'm going to be calling this out in a
lot of the different phases. You want to
learn by doing. And for phase two, that
means building agents with no code. So
at least build one hopefully many
different agents with tools like N8N and
get that experience that comfortability
before then moving on to our next step
which is learning how to use AI coding
assistance. If you are not using AI to
help you code your applications and
automations you are going to fall
behind. Even anthropic the company that
built claude 70% of the code that's
written for their company is written by
AI now. So this is not just hype. The
future of creating software is
definitely humans working alongside AI
with these coding assistants. You have
your AI idees like Windsurf, Cursor,
Rue. These are on your computer
operating in your development
environment. Then you also have
front-end specific builders like lovable
or bolt.diy or bolt.new. These will run
in your browser. It's also very
important to learn how to prompt AI
coding assistance. And so this goes back
to phase one, prompt engineering,
building effective prompts, but also
there's a lot more specific things to be
learned for working with AI coding
assistants specifically. And then also
leveraging MCP servers. I already
mentioned this once, but giving these
extra tools to our AI coding assistants
so they can do things like manage our
database or search the web for
up-to-date documentation. I've got a
video right here where I cover my full
process for using AI coding assistants,
including things like prompting and MCP
servers and setting up global rules as
well, so you can dictate the behavior of
your AI coding assistants. And then as
far as learning by doing, again, going
back to getting very hands-on here,
build out some simple automations and
agents with code. Download one of these
AI idees like Windsurf Cursor or Rue
Code. Build out some simple things. just
get comfortable with using these AI
coding assistants before moving on to
the next step here, which is using code
to create our AI agents now instead of
no code tools. And even if you don't
have a lot of coding experience, I'd
still highly recommend diving into this
phase, especially because of what we had
in the previous phase, using coding
assistance to help in this process. And
that's actually something I cover a lot
in the AI agent mastery course that I
have in the Dynamis community. So check
that out if you're interested. More on
that later. But yes, this phase is just
so important because we can stick to no
code tools like N8N. It's very easy to
use. It gets us started so quickly. I
love using them for prototyping. And you
can take powerful tools like N8N pretty
far. But still, in the end, when you
want the most flexibility, control,
speed, and performance. Generally, I
want to move to building my agents with
code, specifically with Python because
most of our AI agent frameworks like the
ones you see below are using Python.
some JavaScript, mostly Python is the
language for building AI agents. And I'm
not a huge fan of vibe coding. I think
it's important for us to still
understand what is being created through
the AI coding assistance. And so I would
recommend learning the basics of Python
still getting a grasp of programming and
then moving on to picking your AI agent
framework. Like we have Pyantic AI and
Langraph. There are a couple of my
favorites. We got the OpenAI agents SDK.
We have Agno, Crew AI. There are so many
good options out there. So explore, pick
the ones that's right for you based on
simplicity and performance and the
different criteria that you have. But
also do not overthink it. Remember
capabilities not tools. We don't want to
get super ingrained in a specific
framework. We want to learn the higher
leverage skills that will apply no
matter the framework that we end up
using because we don't know if maybe
next month there's going to be some
framework that comes out that just
smashes all the rest of them. So focus
on the higher level capabilities. And we
can do that by applying phases two and
three. Like you learned how to integrate
tools with your agents already and
short-term memory and retrieval augment
generation and using AI coding
assistance. Apply all of that here.
Learn by doing by now moving one of the
agents that you prototyped with a tool
like N8N into a coded version of your
agent using a framework like Pantic AI.
So get that experience, get really
comfortable coding agents and then we
can move on to our next phase which is
advanced architecture. Taking our AI
agents to the next level. This is where
we get into multi- aent workflows and
different architecture patterns for
that. It's just so important for us for
more complex systems to distribute
responsibility between agents just like
it's powerful to distribute
responsibility between people. There's
an anthropic article that I'll link to
below that dives into that. Definitely
worth checking out. And then we also
have other components like memory
systems for long-term memory, guard
rails for input and output, fallback
mechanisms. I have a link to a video
right here where I dive into these
different components. Guardrails is
probably one of the most important ones
though because we have input guardrails,
making sure that we don't have garbage
that's sent to our agent. And then we
have output guardrails, making sure that
there's no garbage that is sent to the
end user. These kind of things are what
is so important to make our AI agents
actually reliable because like I said at
the start versus traditional
automations, AI agents are more powerful
but also a lot more unpredictable. And
so we want to implement things like
guardrails. And so learn by doing. Level
up an agent that you coded in the last
phase. Add in things like long-term
memory or input guard rails. Maybe
combine it with another agent and build
out a multi- aent workflow. just get
that experience, that comfortability,
leveling up your agents to make them
more reliable and more effective. And
then once you get to that point, it is
time to productionize our AI agents.
That brings us to the next phase, which
is deploying our AI agents. And the key
for me for deploying my AI agents to
production is to use a tool called
Docker. This is where I can containerize
my agents into an isolated environment
that I can then deploy anywhere in the
cloud, start getting users using my
agent. There are a lot of cloud
platforms available. So just do your
research, find the one that's right for
you. There are easy to use ones like
Digital Ocean and Hostinger. If you're
an enterprise shop, you'd probably want
to use something more like Amazon Web
Services or the Google Cloud Platform.
If you need a GPU instance to run larger
local large language models, then you
could use something like Vast AI or
RunPod. And I show what this process
looks like in this video right here
where I containerize my agent and then I
deploy it to a platform called Render.
And for you, it's going to look very
similar pretty much no matter which
cloud platform you end up using. And
part of that is in thanks to using
Docker to create a very good standard
for deploying agents. And so learn by
doing by taking this agent that you've
built throughout these phases already
and deploying it to the cloud. Get
comfortable with one of these platforms.
Learn what it takes to build your agent
out. Deploy it, scale it, get it into an
environment for other people to use it.
But once your agent is running in the
wild, it is very important to move on to
the next phase, which is all about
monitoring our agents. This is
oftentimes called agent observability.
It's our way to peer into our AI agent,
which is especially important in
production to see the requests coming in
from our users, the decisions that our
agent is making around tool calling, and
then also the output that's given to our
end users. And this is so crucial for us
to detect any errors with our agents or
just see opportunities to make our AI
agent better. And we'll get into that in
another phase, but being able to
continuously improve our agents is so
crucial. And there are a lot of good
options for agent observability like
Langfuse, Helicone, Langsmith, Logfire,
Impidantic AI. I have this video that
I'll link to right here where I dive
into using Langfuse. It's not that hard
to set up agent observability, but it'll
take your AI agents very, very far. And
like I call it right here, it is 100%
necessary for production. And speaking
of continuously improving our agents,
this brings us on to phase 8, which is
agent evaluation. There is a very
interesting statistic that I've heard
quite a few times recently, actually.
When you are building AI agents, it's
only 25% of the actual coding or
automating. And then the rest of the 75%
is evaluating your AI agent and making
adjustments to improve your agent based
on the evaluating. And this is so
important and also different from
testing. So when we are testing our
agent or just our code in general, we
are testing for general code
correctness. Making sure that our
application isn't going to completely
crash or the end user would not get a
result at all. But evaluating is
different. It's all about agent behavior
correctness. And so if an evaluation
produces a negative result, it doesn't
mean that there's an error or an
application crashed, it just means that
our agent is not giving an acceptable
answer, whatever that might look like.
And there are a lot of different ways to
evaluate agents. We have the whole idea
of LLM as a judge, like using another
large language model to evaluate the
output of our agent. We have task
completion testing. This is more around
tool calling like did the agent invoke
the tools necessary based on this
request to do something like update a
task in a sauna or draft an email in
Gmail whatever that might be. And then
plain and simple we also have human
evaluation having people like maybe
these are our end users that fill out a
survey after they use our platform and
just trying out our agents seeing if the
results are acceptable to them. And
evaluating your agents is really what's
going to take you far. All of the
previous phases are all about building a
reliable agent, building one that's
effective, that does the job, but then
evaluating is where we can make sure
that all of that is actually giving us
the results that we need for the system
that we're trying to build or automate.
And that brings us to the next phase,
which is mastering AI with others. One
of the biggest regrets that I have when
I first started learning AI agents was
not doing it with other people. I was
learning pretty much alone and that did
change eventually but it would have sped
up my process for feeling confident
building AI agents so much if I did it
with other people because mastering AI
agents is not easy. There's so much
power that's given to us with these
LLMs. But with great power comes great
responsibility. There's all that
unpredictability with agents that we
have to deal with. That's why it's so
important to find a community and learn
and collaborate with other people. And
this is just the perfect time for me to
talk about my community, Dynamus AI
Mastery. I've been pouring my heart and
soul into Dynamus over the past month,
making it the perfect place for you to
master AI with other people and
collaborate as well. And you know that I
pour my heart and soul into YouTube as
well. So, I'm doing the exact same
thing, if not more, with Dynamis. And I
have the AI agent mastery course which
is where I go into my full process in
detail for building AI agents from the
planning phase to prototyping with N8N
to building the agent in Python creating
a full front-end application and
deploying it my full process. So
definitely check out dynamus.ai if that
sounds interesting to you. And I already
have hundreds of other early AI adopters
in the community ready to collaborate
with you. daily events like office hours
and workshops and more. AI agent
templates and resources that are
immediately available to you once you
join the community and daily support and
idea sharing. So, so much to offer.
Definitely check out dynamis.ai. And
with that, that brings us to our last
phase, which is leveraging your new
skill set. Honestly, the thing I love
the most about AI agents is just how
versatile of opportunities you have once
you get really good at building them.
You can automate things in your own
business or your own life. You can
create and sell AI agent templates or
frameworks. And that's a really powerful
thing. By the way, creating systems
around your AI agents, packaging up
those and selling those is so lucrative.
You can start an AI automation agency,
which is kind of related to the thing
above, but maybe making more bespoke
solutions. You can build a SAS product
powered by AI agents. You can become an
AI consultant or adviser for different
companies. You can join or start an AI
focused company. Even at the enterprise
level, this experience will just take
you so far. You can teach others through
content creation like I'm doing all the
time. Contribute to open source AI agent
projects. There are so many different
ways that you can leverage this new
expertise. It takes you so far. And it
doesn't matter the industry or the
niche. Everyone needs AI agents. And so
if you go through this full process, you
get to the point where you're confident
building AI agents, you can do anything.
like the world becomes your oyster. And
that's why I'm just so excited every
single day about AI agents. And I'm just
so motivated to continue to put out
things on my YouTube channel here,
starting up Dynamis and building that
out. Everything that I'm doing, I'm just
so motivated because AI agents really is
the future. That's why it's important to
get on this now. So, there you have it.
That's my full process for learning AI
agents if I had to start over today. I
hope you found this really helpful. No
matter if you're a beginner or if you're
already partially through the path and I
just illuminated the next couple of
steps for you. And if you think there's
anything that I'm missing in this path,
please let me know in the comments. I
love to keep working on this because the
most important thing for me is that the
hard lessons that I had to learn and
wasting my time learning things that
weren't important, I want to make sure
that you don't have to deal with that as
well. So, I'm just trying to pass this
on to you. So, if you appreciated this
content, you're looking forward to more
things AI and AI agents, I would really
appreciate a like and a subscribe.